Protect Your Majesty
폐하를 보호하라
Your Majesty
폐하
Quack doctors
돌팔이
They're all quacks
모두 돌팔이야
Drag them all out and behead them
다 끌어내서 참수하라
General, spare us
장군님 살려주십시오
General, please spare us
제발 살려주십시오
Your Majesty's injury has reached the internal organs
폐하께서 폐를 다치신 데다
Coupled with years of managing state affairs
여러 해 동안 국사로 바삐 보내시고
And recent continuous battles
근래엔 또 연거푸 전쟁을 치른지라
Now Your Majesty's body is exhausted
현재 아주 위독한 상태입니다
We truly are powerless
저희도 정말 속수무책입니다
Forget it
됐다
Don't trouble them
이들을 난처하게 하지 마라
Your Majesty
폐하
Find someone
사람을 붙여
Keep them under guard
이들을 감시하고
No one may contact them
아무도 접촉하지 못 하게 하라
Yes
네
Also
그리고
From now on
이제부터
Without my permission
짐의 허락 없이는
Anyone
아무도
May not approach the tent
짐의 장막 10장 이내로
Within ten zhang
접근하면 안 된다
What if the two generals come to request an audience?
두 장군이 뵙기를 청하면요
You say
짐이
I
행군으로
Am exhausted from marching
지쳐서
Everything
모든 건
Will be discussed upon return to court
귀경하여 의논할 거라고 전해라
Now
이제
The central plains are settled
중원이 안정을 되찾고
Shilang is dead
석랑도 죽었으니
Our dynasty
더 이상
Has no more worries
걱정할 것 없다
Soldiers
장병들이여
Should go home
이제 집으로 돌아가자
First month of the 27th year of Longwu
융무 27년 1월
You issue an edict
당신은 둘째 황자
Ordering the Second Prince Sikong Xu to continue guarding Yan Bei
사공욱에게 남아서 연북을 지킬 것을 명하고
The rest of the army returns to court
남은 대군을 이끌고 귀경길에 오릅니다
When reaching the Shuoyang County area
삭양군 일대에 이르렀을 때
The weather became increasingly cold
날씨는 점점 추워지고
You had to rest temporarily in Yiyang City
당신은 익양성에서 잠시 쉬어가기로 합니다
Your Majesty
폐하
The weather is too cold
날씨가 너무 추우니
Not suitable for long outings
밖에 오래 있으면 안 좋습니다
Your health is important
옥체 보존하셔야죠
Have they all arrived?
다들 왔느냐
Yes
네
The people you wish to summon
폐하께서 찾는 사람들이
Are all in the city awaiting your order
다 성안에서 어명을 기다리고 있습니다
Good
그래
At this time, the city lord's residence
이때 성주부는 이미
Has been converted into your temporary residence
당신의 임시 거처가 되었고
All your affairs are managed here
당신의 모든 업무도 이곳에서 처리하게 되었습니다
Years of warfare
오랜 전쟁으로 인해
Your hair has actually shown some silver
어느덧 당신의 머리에도 서리가 내렸는데
Though physically weak
비록 몸은 허약해졌지만
Your eyes still shine with light
당신의 눈은 여전히 빛이 납니다
You know your time is running out
당신은 자신에게 남은 날이 얼마 없다는 것을 압니다
But the newly pacified realm
이제 막 평정된 천하가
Cannot fall into chaos again because of your departure
당신의 부재로 혼란스러워져서는 안 될 터
You must handle everything that follows
떠나기 전에 이 모든 것을 잘 처리해야 합니다
Your Majesty
폐하
Issue orders
명을 전해라